# Yaseswini Neelamraju

yaseswini.1404@gmail.com; yn9w@virginia.edu

A bioinformatics scientist with 5 years of professional experience in analyzing next generation DNA and RNA sequencing data primarily from human subjects diagnosed with cancer. I am committed to developing and applying computational tools to new and/or existing genomic data and contribute to translational research.

## **EDUCATION**

2018 – Present	Ph.D. Candidate
	Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics
	University of Virginia, Charlottesville
	Major: Bioinformatics
	Thesis: Identifying molecular signatures associated with aging in hematological malignancies
2011 – 2013	Masters in Technology, Bioinformatics
2011 – 2013	Department of Biotechnology and Bioinformatics
	University of Hyderabad, India
	Thesis: Integrating disease-gene and protein-protein interactions to identify candidate
	genes for Psoriasis using network theory.
2007 – 2011	Bachelors of Technology, Biotechnology
	Department of Biotechnology
	Sreenidhi Institute of Science and Technology,
	Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University, India

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Jun-Aug,2022	Summer Intern in Predictive Sciences
	Bristol-Myers Squibb, Cambridge, MA
	• Worked on reproducing and applying an existing tumor microenvironment (TME) subtype method to pancreatic cancer data from TCGA
	<ul> <li>Modified the existing TME subtype classification approach to improve the accuracy</li> </ul>
	• Developed a R shiny application implementing existing and improved TME classification method on tumor data
2017 – 2018	Bioinformatics Analyst
	University of Virginia, Charlottesville, USA
	• Identified DNA methylation and transcriptional changes in patients diagnosed and relapsed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML)
	<ul> <li>Contributed to three peer reviewed manuscripts through collaborative research.</li> </ul>
2015 - 2017	Bioinformatics Analyst
	Weill Cornell Medicine, New York, USA

- Identified DNA methylation and transcriptional changes in patients diagnosed and relapsed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML)
- Identified DNA methylation changes contributing to age related changes in TET2 knock down zebrafish developing myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS)

## 2013 – 2015 Research Scholar

Indiana University-Purdue University, Indiana, USA

- Analyzed and identified mutational landscape of RNA binding proteins across 6000 cancer genomics constituting 26 cancer types from TCGA consortium
- Identified splicing alternations contributing to endocrine resistance in breast cancer cell lines in collaborative research with IU School of Medicine.
- Curated RNA binding proteins and their known functional characteristics identified in humans to construct a database useful for researchers in the field

### TEACHING ASSISTANTSHIP

## 2021 – 2022 University of Virginia

Currently mentoring an undergraduate student in learning basics of computational biology.

- Basic programming in R
- Survival analysis

## Spring, 2017 University of Virginia

Teaching assistant for workshops on

- Introduction to R
- Advanced data manipulation in R
- Visualization in R using ggplot2

## **2014** Indiana University Purdue University

Analysis of microarray array using R

## **SKILLS**

- Experience working with human clinical trial data
- Experience working on high performance computing systems
- I have experience working with large genetic, genomic, and clinical datasets identified from TCGA, DepMap, Beat-AML, ENCODE, NCBI GEO, cBioPortal
- Experience in integrative analysis using multiple genomic datasets and clinical information
- Excellent oral and written communicable skills
- Excellent molecular biology background

Sequence analysis	Sequence alignment tools (DNA and protein): BLAST, BLAT, ClustalW
Next generation	Microarray data analysis
sequencing data	Genome Visualization – UCSC genome browser, IGV
analysis	Bulk-RNAseq: FastQC, STAR, HISAT, Salmon, Kallisto, TopHat, Bowtie,
	Differential gene expression analysis (DESeq2), Gene co-expression networks
	(WGCNA), Deconvolution analysis methods for bulkRNAseq - CIBERSORT
	RNA-splicing: rMATS
	DNA methylation (Bisulphite sequencing): Methylkit, MethylSig, Integrative
	analysis with gene expression data
	ChIP-seq: MACS, Differential peak analysis using DESeq2
<b>Functional genomics</b>	Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA), single sample Gene set enrichment
	analysis (ssGSEA), Gene set variation analysis (GSVA), Ingenuity Pathway
	analysis (IPA), EnrichR, GProfileR, GREAT (Genomic Regions Enrichment
	of Annotations Tool), Transcription factor binding analysis (HOMER, MEME
	suite of tools).
Systems biology	Network analysis using igraph R package

Biostatistics	Application of statistical tests to genomic data, Survival analysis, Cox
2105000250105	proportional hazards model, Correlation
Machine Learning	Principal Component analysis, K-means clustering, Hierarchical clustering,
	Linear models, Logistic regression, Generalized linear regression methods,
	principal component regression (PCR), partial least squares regression (PLS),
	Xtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost)
<b>Operating Systems</b>	Linux, Mac OS and Windows
Scripting/Programming	C (beginner), Perl, R, Python . Experience working in conda environment
Languages	
Version Control	GitHub, R markdown
Workflow Management	Nextflow (Beginner)
Web development	HTML, CSS, RShiny, GitHub Pages

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1. <u>Yaseswini Neelamraju</u>, Evisa Gjini, Sagar Chhangawala, Hao Fan, Shuning He, Chang-Bin Jing, Ashley T Nguyen, Subhash Prajapati, Caroline Sheridan, Yariv Houvras, Ari Melnick, A.Thomas Look, Francine Garrett-Bakelman. "Depletion of tet2 results in age-dependent changes in DNA methylation and gene expression in a zebrafish model of myelodysplastic syndrome". (*Accepted for publication in Frontiers in Hematology*)
- Rapaport, F., K. Seier, Y. Neelamraju, D. Hassane, T. Baslan, D. T. Gildea, S. Haddox, T. Lee, H. M. Murdock, C. Sheridan, A. Thurmond, L. Wang, M. Carroll, L. D. Cripe, H. Fernandez, C. E. Mason, E. Paietta, G. J. Roboz, Z. Sun, M. S. Tallman, Y. Zhang, M. Gonen, R. Levine, A. M. Melnick, M. Kleppe and F. E. Garrett-Bakelman (2022). "Integrative analysis identifies an older female-linked AML patient group with better risk in ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group's clinical trial E3999." Blood Cancer J 12(9): 137.
- 3. Barreyro, L., A. M. Sampson, C. Ishikawa, K. M. Hueneman, K. Choi, M. A. Pujato, S. Chutipongtanate, et al. "Blocking Ube2n Abrogates Oncogenic Immune Signaling in Acute Myeloid Leukemia." Sci Transl Med 14, no. 635 (Mar 9 2022): eabb7695.
- 4. Rapaport F, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Baslan T, Hassane D, Gruszczynska A, Robert de Massy M, et al. Genomic and evolutionary portraits of disease relapse in acute myeloid leukemia. Leukemia. 2021.
- 5. Olson TL, Cheon H, Xing JC, Olson KC, Paila U, Hamele CE, et al. Frequent somatic TET2 mutations in chronic NK-LGL leukemia with distinct patterns of cytopenias. Blood. 2021;138(8):662-73.
- 6. Abshiru NA, Sikora JW, Camarillo JM, Morris JA, Compton PD, Lee T, et al. Targeted detection and quantitation of histone modifications from 1,000 cells. PLoS One. 2020;15(10):e0240829.
- 7. Gokmen-Polar Y, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Goswami CP, Gu Y, Gu X, Nallamothu G, et al. Splicing factor ESRP1 controls ER-positive breast cancer by altering metabolic pathways. EMBO Rep. 2019;20(2).
- 8. <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Gonzalez-Perez A, Bhat-Nakshatri P, Nakshatri H, Janga SC. Mutational landscape of RNA-binding proteins in human cancers. RNA Biol. 2018;15(1):115-29.
- 9. Nishtala S, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC. Dissecting the expression relationships between RNA-binding proteins and their cognate targets in eukaryotic post-transcriptional regulatory networks. Sci Rep. 2016; 6:25711.
- 10. <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Hashemikhabir S, Janga SC. The human RBPome: from genes and proteins to human disease. J Proteomics. 2015;127(Pt A):61-70.
- 11. Hashemikhabir S, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC. Database of RNA binding protein expression and disease dynamics (READ DB). Database (Oxford). 2015;2015: bav072.
- 12. Gokmen-Polar Y, Vladislav IT, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Janga SC, Badve S. Prognostic impact of HOTAIR expression is restricted to ER-negative breast cancers. Sci Rep. 2015; 5:8765.

- 13. Gokmen-Polar Y, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Goswami CP, Gu X, Nallamothu G, Janga SC, et al. Expression levels of SF3B3 correlate with prognosis and endocrine resistance in estrogen receptor-positive breast cancer. Mod Pathol. 2015;28(5):677-85.
- 14. Chaturvedi P, <u>Neelamraju Y</u>, Arif W, Kalsotra A, Janga SC. Uncovering RNA binding proteins associated with age and gender during liver maturation. Sci Rep. 2015; 5:9512.

## **PRESENTATIONS**

2023	"A pro-inflammatory gene signature characterizes a better risk aged AML patient group in ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group's clinical trial E3999" – Lightning talk and poster presentation
	FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference, FASEB, August 2023
2021	"Identifying molecular determinants of sex associated outcomes in acute myeloid leukemia patients over the age of 60" – Poster presentation
	Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics Department Retreat, October 2021
2021	"An integrative analysis identifies a female-linked group that associates with better risk for AML patients older than sixty years of age in a clinical trial of the ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group (E3999)" – poster presentation
	FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference, FASEB, July 2021 (Virtual conference)
2021	"An integrative classifier identifies as sex-associated outcome risk in AML patients older than
	sixty years of age" – Oral presentation
	Biomedical data science research club, April 2021
2019	"Sex based differences in clinical outcomes of Acute Myeloid Leukemia patients over the age of 60"
	Biochemistry and Molecular Genetics Department Retreat, October 2019
2017	"AMLs with high methylation in GADD45A promoter exhibit distinct molecular profiles associated with poor outcome" – oral presentation
	1st Annual Commonwealth of Virginia Cancer Research Conference 2017, Charlottesville
2015	"Mutational landscape of RNA Binding Proteins in human cancer" – poster presentation Systems Biology: Global regulation of Gene Expression Meeting, 2015, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory.

## CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS

2014

2023	FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference
2023	Bio Hackathon organized by St Jude's Children's Research Hospital
2021	FASEB, The Hematologic Malignancies Conference
2020	Biomedical Data Science (Virtual conference) – CSHL
2016	EpiWorkshop jointly organized by Weill Cornell Medicine, Hospital for Special Surgery and
	New York City College of Technology
2015	Advances in Genome Science, NYC Illumina User Group Meeting 2015.
2015	Great Lakes Bioinformatics Conference
2015	Systems Biology: Global regulation of Gene Expression, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory

"The human RBPome: from genes and proteins to human disease" – poster presentation

Rustbelt RNA Meeting, 2014, Pittsburg, PA

## 2014 Rustbelt RNA Meeting

## HONORS, AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIP

2023 UVA's Cancer Center trainee travel award to attend the hematologic malignancies conference

organized by FASEB

2015 Stipend award to attend the Cold Spring Laboratory Meeting on "Systems Biology: Global

regulation of Gene Expression" held in Puerto Rico during 28th Jan, 15 - 01st Feb, 15)

2011 SNIST-ISTE Gold medal for securing first rank amongst the students of B.Tech Biotechnology

Class of 2011.

2007-2010 Academic excellence awards while pursuing Bachelors in Biotechnology for the years 2007 -

2010.

## ACADEMIC VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

2022	Participated in the Skill2Give event organized by Bristol-Myers Squibb (BMS)
<b>2021 – Current</b>	Co-organizer of CPHG (Center for Public Health Genomics) computing club.

2022 BMG recruitment, UVA student host for 1 weekend

**2019 – 2020** BMG recruitment, UVA, *student* host for 1-2 weekends per year

2019-2020 Volunteer Coordinator at Society for the Promotion of Indian Classical Music and Culture

Amongst Youth (SPICMACAY), UVA Chapter

2019 Participated in the data hackathon organized by the UVA Biomedical Data Sciences

Training Program

2017-2018 Volunteer at Society for the Promotion of Indian Classical Music and Culture Amongst

Youth (SPICMACAY), UVA Chapter

### WEBSITE

LinkedIn: Yaseswini Neelamraju | LinkedIn

Google Scholar: <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=wzrrprAAAAAJ">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=wzrrprAAAAAJ</a>

#### **HOBBIES**

Hiking and trail walking with my dog; gardening; cooking; photography and learning all things creative!